actually a pretty diverse different set
of staking pools and if you zoom into
either of the top items on the uh chart
on the top left so Lio and it has
somewhere somewhere a little bit under
30% but then actually Lio is like it's
not one actor right it's a dow
technically the deposits are split
between 40 different node operators
approximately and there's some more
complicated structure that keeps
updating uh but it's so I think it's
reasonable to think of it as being like
somewhere between one actor and 40
actors exactly where like this is like a
problem for you social science people to
figure out right how do you actually
quantify the decentralization thing
there are there there's even grant
opportunities for this stuff so that's
uh like so that's number one right and
then number two unidentified now
unidentified is not an actor just like
there's no the any key on your keyboard
is not actually a key so unidentified
like we actually don't know what it is
there's probably lots of solo stakers
lots of small business stakers lots of
uh various tiny staking pools also not
one actor right so ethereum L1 today
actually has a surprisingly High degree
of decentralization in its proof of
stake design and this is a property that
I think has only gotten better over
time here is one thing one property that
actually has gotten a lot better so
ethereum uh about uh 5 years ago was
basically just gu right and when you
have an ecosystem that is dominated by
one client that itself becomes a central
point of failure right so who here
remembers the 2016 dos
attacks
yay so you know remember wake up 5:17
a.m. get a military style wakeup call um
you know say Hey you have to go down to
you know like the thing that we suddenly
turned into a war room now go down and
then oh someone discovered a bug in the
clients now the entire chain is stopped
and then we fix it and then two 3 days
later the the some guy somewhere finds
another bug and then 3 Days Later
another bug and then that keeps going on
for a whole month until eventually uh we
have to hard Fork but during that period
actually the ability for ethereum to
have two different clients at the time
they were gu and parody basically saved
the chain there were like there were
times when there was a bug that would
hit gu but not parody there were times
when there was a bug that would hit
parody but not gu um and uh so ethereum
actually gained a lot from having
multiple software implementations and
this is something that as of 2024 is
probably at the best that it's ever been
in ethereum's history
so so on the left you have consensus
clients consensus clients handle the
proof of stake part of ethereum on the
right you have execution clients
execution clients handle the evm part of
ethereum so as we we can see the single
client with the highest market share is
gu which is like somewhere around 50%
and actually this is uh from a source
that's basically assuming that most
unidentified clients are gu and so it
could easily be below 50% right so let's
say it's about 50 so what happens if
there is a bug in any ethereum client
like literally today right now okay
anyone here has like a
bug okay uh Josh can you check as
ethereum still running
I'm going to guess it is um you know bet
like 99.99% Plus on poly Market okay
so what so case one what happens if the
client is gu that's the worst case if
the client is gu and there's a bug what
realistically happens basically chain
splits in half one half follows gu one
half follows the other clients but on
both sides the chain stops finalizing to
finalize you need 23 if you have less
than 23 the chain keeps blocks keep
getting created but the chain stop
finalizing and so if you are a user an
application a business and you're
waiting for confirmation on some
transaction you're you're probably
actually going to be waiting for a
finality and so if the chain splits in
half because of a client bug well
actually your neither chain is going to
finalize and so you're going to detect
that and you're going to be on standby
what's realistically going to happen
cord davs get on high alert figure out
which client actually has the bug and
the bug gets fixed the one time this
happened in ethereum actually yeah fun
fact I actually set the transaction that
did it myself this was back in 2016 uh
basically everything was fixed within 12
hours so that's the worst case every
other case basically if prism and
Lighthouse have a bug all that happens
is that ethereum stops finalizing for
like about a day at most and then it B
it just goes back to normal any other
client you're you're not going to notice
anything at all so in terms of practical
decentralization having multiple clients
is extremely helpful and also having
multiple clients is extremely helpful
because it diversifies the power and the
control over the uh eorum ecosystem
especially in any kind of contentious
situation right if some kind of Dow Fork
type incident happened again and one
particular development team made a
choice is unpopular then even if that
one uh that one development team just
insists on pushing it through users are
going to be very easily able to just
switch to the other clients and just
completely route around them this is not
something that is anywhere close to that
practical in a single client ecosystem
having a diverse multi client ecosystem
is actually very difficult to achieve I
think aside from ethereum no other chain
has really gotten to achieved anything
close to this and even outside of
ethereum like even web browsers web
browsers supposed to be an open standard
reality is like something like 80% of